Hi, welcome back to Nagarjuna.
Arya Nagarjuna.
We're moving on to Chapter 11.
Look, the chapter 10 was tough.
That fire and firewood thing is so tough.
Does the fire make the firewood
or does the firewood make the fire?
And I'm happy to say that we're moving on
to a chapter where the
first verse is easier.
MA YIN DGAG
[everyone laughs]
So this chapter is called
SNGON DANG PHYI MA'I MTHA' BRTAG PA
BRTAG PA in Tibetan means
"pariksha" means "an
investigation", right?
And then SNGON DANG PHYI MA'I MTHA' means:
is there a front end on sansara?
And is there a back end on sansara?
And that's a very intriguing question.
I called the chapter name,
"An Investigation of a First Beginning,
or a Final Ending, to Things".
Is there a first beginning?
And is there a final ending to things?
So we're going to talk about that.
I think if you're bored and
you want to go deeper...
I think it's very
interesting to try to see
why he went in this order.
It seems like he's just
throwing stuff out.
Almost without logic.
But I think there's a deeper logic.
If you could understand why
the 27 go in the order they do,
maybe you could understand
the Nargarjuna's mind somehow.
And again, Choney Lama,
as you remember from our first session,
way back two years ago,
he just mixes it all up.
He says, "The real order
is like Chapter 18 first,
and then..."
Here's the first verse in Chapter 11:
,SNGON MTHA' MNGON NAM ZHES ZHUS TSE,
Let's just talk about that first line.
It's very beautiful.
SNGON MTHA' means a first beginning
to sansara,
a first beginning to our
time in this universe.
Was there a point where
you and me first came
into this universe?
Was there a beginning
point of Michael, or Pachi,
or Tim, or Rebecca, or Pau?
Was there a first...
Was there a beginning point?
ZHUS TSE means "when they asked him."
When they asked him. Who?
They asked Buddha.
When his disciples asked Buddha.
ZHES - "quote mark."
"Is there a first beginning to things?
Was there first beginning to things?"
ZHUS TSE
Past tense ZHUS to make a request
or to ask.
ZHUS TSE
Now, I think it's fascinating
that they didn't say YOD.
Okay, Tim for a hundred bucks.
Yes, a hundred bucks.
Why didn't they say to Buddha,
"Is there a first beginning to things?"
They said, "Is the first
beginning to things evident?"
MNGON
Like Abhidharma.
It means "visible" or "manifest."
They didn't ask Buddha,
"Is there a first beginning
to the universe or to our
career in the universe?"
"Is there a beginning
which is MNGON, which is evident?"
[student mumbles]
Yes, good, hundred dollars for Rebecca.
Okay.
[student mumbling]
Hundred bucks for Rebecca, yes.
It means, Can you see? You see?
They didn't say, "Is there a beginning?"
They said, "Can you close your
eyes and just check for us?"
Is it MNGON?
It's very sexy to me that
Nagarjuna chose this verb.
Can you see a beginning?
Which means "is there?"
But they didn't say, "Is there?"
They said, "Can you see a beginning?"
ZHUS TSE
THUB PA CHEN POS - The Great Able One,
meaning the Buddha, Mahamuni.
MIN - nope. Nope.
"No. I can't see any
beginning to all this mess.
It's beginningless."
,'KHOR BA THOG MA MTHA' MED DE,
There's no first beginning
of sansara circle.
And there's no... MTHA' MED
means "there's no end" either.
Now that's something we got to talk about.
DE LA... And then they said, "Why not?"
And he said, "Well,
nothing has a front end
and a back end and a middle."
Don't ask me if your career in sansara
had a beginning and the past,
had a first beginning and a final end.
Why?
Because nothing has a front end
and nothing has a back end
and nothing has a middle.
DE LA SNGON...
But he doesn't say it that way.
He says, ,GANG LA THOG MED MTHA' MED PAR,
anything that doesn't have
a front end and a back end,
DBUS NI GA LA YOD
how could you have a middle?
If the place you're going,
if the road you're going
to travel is infinite,
if the road you have traveled is infinite,
I don't know, where is the middle?
Where are you going to put the middle?
He's like, "Come on, where's the middle?"
I like this picture of a ribbon.
Somehow it suggests to me the difficulty
of defining a beginning.
I don't know, I just saw
this picture and I thought,
"Oh wow, that's the one I want."
There's no middle place
on an endless line.
Let's go to the next verse.
[coughs] Sorry. [coughs] Sorry.
,DE PHYIR DE LA SNGA PHYI DANG,
,LHAN CIG RIM PA MI 'THAD DO,
That SNGA PHYI means "earlier and later."
But Choney Lama explains that Nagarjuna
has now gone on to your lifetimes.
Your lifetimes.
There's no earlier lifetime.
And there's no later lifetime.
There's also no place...
LHAN CIG means where the two meet.
Here it means where the two meet.
There's no place where all your past lives
meets all your future lives.
There's no place where you are living now.
There's no place you're going
to live in your future lives.
There's no place you have
lived in your past lives.
And there's no meeting point between
your past lives and your future lives.
So don't ask me about a beginning.
By the way, did he really say, no?
Do you remember?
LUNG MA BSTAN BCU BZHI
14, LUNG MA BSTAN 14 unanswered questions.
I believe this is one
of them, or two of them.
He refused to answer.
And then later as his disciples said,
"Why you refuse to answer the question?"
He said, "Any answer I give
they're going to misunderstand it.
It's better to keep my mouth shut."
And that applies to a
talking to the press,
and stuff like that.
Anything you say is going to be twisted.
Just no, thank you.
I found this other picture,
Okay, Pachi,
of a guy with a rope.
Yes.
It means the beginning
is almost undefinable
and the end is undefinable.
That's okay. No, it's worse than that.
The middle is also undefinable.
You can't find present moment.
It's bad enough
that your lifetimes have no beginning.
And it's bad enough
that your lifetimes have no end.
But by the way,
there's no place where
you are between those two.
That's why the rope is unraveling. Get it?
All right, we're going to go on to...
It's kind of a denial of
past lives and future lives.
Technically, it's called that.
,GAL TE SKYE BA SNGA GYUR LA,
,RGA SHI PHYI MA YIN NA NI,
So which came first: your
birth, or your aging and death?
In one put it together.
Which came first: your birth,
or your aging and death?
Which came first?
GAL TE SKYE BA SNGA GYUR LA
If your birth came first,
RGA SHI PHYI MA YIN NA NI
and then your aging and death came later,
SKYE BA RGA SHI MED PA DANG
then you should be able
to have a birth with no aging and death.
Because in the early part,
it has to stand by itself.
If you can have a birth with
no getting old and dying,
Sorry. If birth came before
getting old and dying,
then birth can be self-standing.
And it doesn't have to depend
on getting old and dying.
If you say, "My rebirth
into this world came first,
then I got old in this world and died."
He says, "No, okay if
that's the way it happened,
"then SKYE BA RGA SHI MED PA DANG
"then you can have a rebirth
"that doesn't have getting old and dying."
MA SHI BAR YANG SKYE BAR 'GYUR
And you could be born without dying.
MA SHI BAR
Without dying, you could be born.
If being born comes before
getting old and dying,
then you could have a being born
without an aging and dying,
and you could live without
getting old and dying.
Are they interdependent?
Does one depend on the other?
That what is the question.
GAL TE SKYE BA 'PHYI 'GYUR LA
Then the guy says, the guy
is like, a perfect fall guy.
He always gives the right wrong answer.
And he says, "Oh, oh, GAL
TE SKYE BA 'PHYI 'GYUR LA"
The birth comes after aging and death.
and RGA SHI SNGA BA YIN NA NI
Aging and death come first.
And then you die and you get reborn.
So rebirth is not first.
Getting old and dying comes first.
Then you have a rebirth.
,SKYE BA MED PA'I RGA SHI NI,
,RGYU MED PAR NI JI LTAR 'GYUR,
Okay, good.
So, in the beginning of that process,
when there's just getting old and dying,
that doesn't depend on anything.
You can get old and
die without being born.
- Why? - Being born comes later.
Okay, so you can get old and
die without being born, right?
- Why? - Well, you said
the being born comes later.
He can't change his story.
He can't say being born comes
before getting old and dying
because he said being born comes after
getting gold and dying. Got it?
He started out with
beginning born comes first
and getting old and dying comes later.
But then there was a problem
that you could get born and never die.
Because it would be by itself
and then you'd have it.
And we have a birth here.
I was looking for a baby to be born.
Oh, there it is, my grandson,
Maitri.
A birth with a birth would have no death.
A birth that was just a
birth would have no death.
He came out like that, by the way.
He was already, looks
like Rodin's "Thinker".
Did you ever see that, Pachi, in Paris?
Rodin, his estate?
That's awesome. That guy is up there,,,
That's Maitri.
Next verse.
,SKYE BA DANG NI RGA SHI DAG,
,LHAN CIG RUNG BA MA YIN TE,
,SKYE BZHIN PA NA 'CHI 'GYUR ZHING,
,GNYIS KA RGYU MED CAN DU 'GYUR,
Then the guy again,
He's trying to get out of the problems.
And he says, "You know what?
"You're born, and get old
and die at the same time.
"Don't say one came before the other.
"Because when you say
one came before the other
"there's all these problems."
Then the one that came before the other
would have to not depend on the other one.
So I'll tell you what:
both at the same time.
You're born and you die at the same time.
Then Nagarjuna says,
LHAN CIG RUNG BA MA YIN TE
That's not right.
SKYE BZHIN PA NA 'CHI 'GYUR ZHING
Then a baby coming out of the womb
would be dying at the
moment. Not possible.
GNYIS KA RGYU MED CAN DU 'GYUR
And since neither came first,
they would both be causeless.
There would be no born
before getting old and dying.
And there'd be no getting old and dying
that caused you to be reborn.
Because they were
happening at the same time.
Therefore, both would be causeless.
By the way, anytime something is causeless
there's a problem. Why?
It could pop up anywhere all the time.
Oh, look, there's death.
Oh, look, there's aging.
It'd be happening,
boop, boop, boop, boop, all around you.
Can being born and dying happen
at the same time? Picture...
Yes. I don't know.
Let's skip to the next one.
Veronica's looking over my shoulder,
"What are you doing with
that picture?" Nevermind.
She gave up a long time
ago trying to figure out
why I spend all day
finding weird pictures.
Here we go. Next one.
,GANG LA SNGA PHYI LHAN CIG GI,
,RIM PA DE DAG MI SRID PA'I,
,SKYE BA RE DANG RGA SHI DE,
,CI YI PHYIR NA SPRO BAR BYED,
This is very, very,
very interesting to me.
Look, so birth can't come
before getting old and dying.
Right?
Right.
And getting old and dying
can't come before being born.
Right.
And we said they can't happen
at the same time, right?
Right.
So they're MI SRID PA'I, right?
What's MI SRID PA'I, Tim, do you remember?
So they're impossible. Right?
And the guy says, "Yes,
they're impossible."
Then Nagarjuna says, "Well,
why the hell you keep
talking about being born,
and dying and getting old?"
[Chuckles] CI'I PHYIR
Why you make up this crap?
SPRO BAR means...
Now we got to talk about SPROS PA.
SPRO BAR means why you
make up all this stuff?
Why you keep coming up with weird stuff?
- Oh, first I was born, then
I got old and dead.    - No.
- Oh, I got old and dead, and
then I got born again.   - No.
- Oh, they happened at the
same time.   - No, no, no.
[chuckles] Then why you keep
thinking of this weird stuff?
So "weird stuff, thinking of weird stuff,
There's a special word.
SPROS PA
And I wanted to talk about it.
Because to me it's very interesting.
What's the Sanskrit for
thinking up weird stuff?
What's the verb? Here we go.
We're going to go to the Sanskrit again,
which is prapancha.
Prapancha. And it's weird.
And you're not going to
be comfortable with it.
[student mutters]
No, it's hard to find.
And there's a lot of things it could be.
So pra- means "forward",
like the prow of a boat, or
a proud person, or forward.
So the pra- part is easy.
The hard part is √pañc.
It can have several meanings.
What's pancha?
Yes, fire.
√pañc means fire.
Pancha means fire.
Then it came into German's "fünf."
√Pañc changes to "fünf."
And then it came into English as fire.
What is it in Spanish?
- Fuego.
- Oh, then forget that.
That's a weird thing, which probably
means it was %kavanch before.
But that's a long story.
So prapancha.
I take it to be like this.
Look...[shows hand movement]
And the many comes from the one.
So why you keep making up stuff?
Why you keep making up stuff
when there's nothing there?
Why you SPROS PA?
SPROS PA means that [shows
hand movement] also.
Or √pac...
Do you know √pac?
Like Pachi. [chuckles]
The verb in Sanskrit,
√pac, means "to cook", to cook something.
It used to be pekw- (Indo-European root).
And then that came into
kitchen and cucina.
And vipaka,
means when your karma is cooked.
That means karmic ripening.
And the Sanskrit word for karmic ripening
is super cook, vipaka, vipac.
That cooking can also have the feeling
of setting the dishes out on the table,
like setting a meal up for a person.
So again, it's this idea
of... [shows hand movement]
Why did you make up this feast?
Why you keep making up
birth, aging, death?
Why you keep telling me this?
Why you keep making up this stuff?
Like presenting a meal.
[student mumbles] Yes, that too.
There's also another
meaning to the Sanskrit,
which is √pek.
And √pek in Indo-European
means to be pretty,
to be beautiful.
And it comes from a verb for combing sheep
and combing your hair and
making yourself beautiful.
So it's called √pek.
√pek also means to pick
out hair from a sheep
and to make a sheep beautiful.
And that √pekt came into the word "fight."
That's why there's a GH and fight,
which means pulling
somebody's hair. [chuckles]
And there's a kind of
shell called "pectin,"
which looks like a fan.
So again, you get this idea
of... [shows hand movement]
creating reality from a single point,
in many different versions.
Why are we discussing this verb?
- [Student] Thinking of weird things?
- Yes. Nagarjuna says,
"Come on, I'm tired of it.
Quit pecking, quit picking
on, pecking on me."
Like, leave it alone, all right?
Why you keep making up
these different things?
- So what if sansara have a beginning,
then sansara will have
an end, that sansara...
- Just stop making up
crap. Ok? It doesn't.
This is all your... [shows hand movement].
√pac.
Stop the Sanskrit lesson.
The difference between making
something out of nothing
and making something out of something.
And that's a magician here.
And I chose this picture
because there is a
SPROS PA which is legal.
Nagarjuna's accusing the guy
of making up false things:
Beginning to things,
end to things, middle?
Stop making up stuff.
But then if you're Nagarjuna, you say,
"But by the way, you do always
make up stuff." [Laughs]
Yes, but at least if you
know what you're doing,
you're not making it up that bad. [Laughs]
So yes, we are creating reality.
There's a verb in Tibetan, RIS SU CHAD PA
which means "to separate hairs",
which means to define reality.
And that you are doing.
You are peka, Pachi, you
are creating reality.
You are drawing lines and
all... This is where Tim starts.
This is where Tim's computer starts.
You are making those lines.
But that's not what I'm talking about.
I'm talking about your human need to say
there was a beginning to your lifetimes
and then there is a final lifetime.
There's not. Your mind goes on infinitely.
And it has no beginning and no end.
And philosophically, you
cannot find the present moment.
Although it feels like there's one.
Next verse.
If you're not confused yet
you haven't been listening.
,'KHOR BA 'BA' ZHIG SNGON GYI MTHA',
,YOD MA YIN PAR MA ZAD KYI,
,RGYU DANG 'BRAS BU NYID DANG NI,
,MTSAN NYID DANG NI MTSAN GZHI NYID,
,TSOR DANG TSOR PO NYID DANG NI,
,DON YOD GANG DAG CI YANG RUNG,
,DNGOS RNAMS THAMS CAD NYID LA YANG,
,SNGON GYI MTHA' NI YOD MA YIN,
Look, 'KHOR BA 'BA' ZHIG
means it's not just sansara
that's the problem.
'BA' ZHIG means "only."
Last chapter. The Yoga Sutra.
Fifty dollars.
[student mumbles]
[GMR Chuckles]
It's called 'BA' ZHIG PA
TThe one and only.
Kaivailya.
The oldest yoga center in India
is called Kaivalya.
The Center for the One and
Only Beginning of All Things
or something like that. Kaivalya.
And it became a synonym for
emptiness in the Yoga Sutra.
The one and only, 'BA' ZHIG
What's it doing here, Geshe-La?
Stop getting distracted.
'KHOR BA 'BA' ZHIG means...
Look, it's not just
sansara that doesn't have
a beginning and an end.
MA ZAD means it's not only that.
RGYU DANG 'BRAS BU NYID DANG NI
You cannot point to a first cause.
You cannot point to a final result.
MTSAN NYID DANG NI MTSAN GZHI NYID
You cannot point to a first
mental picture of something.
And you can't point to the first thing
that matched that mental picture.
Definition and definiendum.
TSOR DANG TSOR PO NYID DANG NI
You cannot point to the first
feeling that was ever felt.
Every feeling felt something.
And everything that was felt
came from a previous feeling.
DON YOD GANG DAG CI YANG RUNG
DON YOD means something which has meaning,
but it means substantial
or something concrete.
You can't point to
anything in the universe.
GANG DAG CI YANG RUNG
,DNGOS RNAMS THAMS CAD NYID LA YANG,
,SNGON GYI MTHA' NI YOD MA YIN,
There is no beginning to any
experience in the universe.
Forget it.
Nagarjuna's like, "Don't ask me."
Don't ask Buddha "did your
past lives have a beginning?"
Why?
Because when you hurt your finger
it didn't have beginning either.
So forget your universe.
Pick your nose. It didn't
have a beginning either.
He said, "Stop asking me,
stop making up this stuff."
So this verse about...
Look, sansara doesn't have any beginning,
but neither does cause and effect,
neither does definition,
neither does sensation.
Nothing has a beginning. That's Nagarjuna.
That's when was the first mantra?
When did the mantra begin?
When did the cancer start
to get healed by the mantra?
And if you don't understand those things,
it's not going to work as well.
All right.
- Oh but it's too difficult
to understand those things.
Or my grandmother will
never understand it,
Geshe-la, just let her do the mantras.
- That's okay. If your grandma is 95...
I have a lady I take care of.
This is our conversation.
I'll say, "Hi, how you doing?"
She say, "Mike, how are you?"
I say, "Fine." She say,
"What are you up to?"
I'll say, "You know,
I've been filming stuff
with Pachi and Tim."
And then she'll go, "Oh, that's nice.
"Oh, Mike! What are you up to nowadays?"
And she'll just ask me the same question
over and over again.
And it's interesting,
me and Veronica read a book about
how to answer older people.
And it said, never say,
you asked me that 10 times today already,
because they already
feel bad about being old
and not remembering anything.
So never get impatient,
just answer nicely.
And then that book said,
how you answer nicely
is a sign of your mental health. [Laughs]
You can change and make
it more interesting.
"Oh, me and Pachi went out for pizza,
and we had a..."
And then the third time
she asks you can say
"Oh, me and Rebecca came from LA..."
And she's like, "Wow."
So why am I saying that?
I don't remember. [Laughs]
- [Student] Don't teach
your grandma mantras
when she's not...
- Yes. Yes. Yes.
If someone is that far gone... Okay.
Just teach them mantra.
Tell them to do the mantra.
Don't try to explain how the mantra works.
I believe that if a person's over 95,
don't explain the mantra. In my opinion,
before that, always explain the mantra.
Because it will work better.
So unless their mind is that far gone.
By the way, even a 95 year old,
if you try to explain emptiness to them,
you can get some really sexy results.
You can get some amazing results.
My own mother, my stepmother...
I was visiting her,
and I said, "Well,
let's go out for lunch."
She said, "I can't," and I said "Why?"
And she said, "I got a yoga class."
And I was like, "What? You're doing yoga?"
And she's 94, right? She's
doing chair yoga or something.
I said, "Wow, that's so great, Mom,
I didn't know you were doing yoga."
She said, "I've been doing
yoga for 30 years, every day."
And I'm like, "Oh my
gosh, I didn't know that.
How'd you get started in yoga?"
"You taught me my first class, you forgot.
And then I never stopped."
And I just didn't know.
So it can be a surprise.
You can try to explain the deeper meaning
of how mantra works.
The only person you can't explain to is
if they're totally... a
hundred years old or something.
But anybody else will
benefit from some explanation
of what's going on with the mantra.
No beginning, no middle
to all these things.
And we have an infinity sign.
It's just to make the class
more interesting for you.
It looks like a car, right? A car.
But don't try to find the starting point.
Don't try to find where you're at now.
There isn't any, by itself.
All right, let's go ahead.
Oh, oh my gosh.
We finished the class. Is
that possible? [Chuckles]
That was a short one.
By the way, that's the whole
chapter, I'm sorry. Is it?
Am I crazy? Oh, no I am...
No, I'm not crazy. That's all.
That's all. Don't try to find it.
Look. Do your past lives
have beginning? No.
Do your past lives have a final end? No.
Why are we talking about that?
Because nothing else does either.
This class doesn't have an end.
This class doesn't have a beginning.
This class doesn't have a
halfway point, from its own side.
If you see this class end suddenly,
it's because your seeds ran out.
Nothing has an end of its own.
Nothing has a beginning of it's own.